[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to me that what I do is, like, when I realize, like, remember the present moment, some kind of impression, myself, whatever, include myself in the present, and then I try to
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the thing is, if something is abstract or intellectual, that is determined by your attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your attitude determines whether it's going to be abstracted from the present experience or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you know how to look at it properly, then nothing is abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even terms like the infinite space and either perception or no perception become state that mind can get established upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not divorced from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I redeveloped the knowledge of them, so it can get established in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, for somebody who has absolutely no concept, no recognition of it, it is... it will remain abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point, like, in simpler terms, for what you're trying to do, eh... Well, first of all, as I said, you can't force the background as a foreground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that means something else is the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can only just recognize whatever is the foreground at a time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, while foreground is present, simultaneously with the present foreground, you start discerning the background, well, very thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_00]: in regard to that foreground, but not over-intending the background, not looking at the background directly, because then that becomes foreground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just attended it, which means then something else is peripheral to your attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's so hard, because you can't attend both ends simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would require you to step away from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only attend one.
[SPEAKER_00]: while the other is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why nāmarūpa determines viññāṇa when you look at viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Viññāṇa determines nāmarūpa if you look at nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't look at them both and see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, none of this is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can only learn, while you're looking at nāmarūpa, for example, to discern the presence of viññāṇa, in this sense, or just discern the periphery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without stopping, without ceasing to look at nāmarūpa or whatever you've chosen, to look at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you develop knowledge about the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowledge that that too is determined by the foreground.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm looking in as much as the foreground is determined by the background that is being generated by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't look at it to the same extent and compare the two and say, okay, these both are mine, not self, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why that's why it's so hard to... that's why it has to be
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be sort of repeated on and on and on and on and off, because it's not like you're figuring it out intellectually, nor is it some sort of a mystical experience where you just wait for some revelation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a mental drill, whereby you lock your mind, literally, to like a standstill for a second, for a two, and you keep doing it, and you keep doing it, and you keep doing it, until you start discerning right what's there in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you just said was that you're afraid you might become intellectual and sort of not really... That's probably true in your case, because what, only three days ago you heard about it, so it's going to take time to develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, however, even if you're talking to yourself, so to speak, it is slightly a crude manner of maintaining a mindfulness, but you wouldn't be able to talk about things if they're not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you... even your talking to yourself is actually generated from the present situation, things you're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's only your attitude, then, that makes it kind of divorced from being... remaining rooted in the present situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start talking to yourself presently, you become mindful of
[SPEAKER_00]: What you're doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Talking to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: About these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're not... and again, it's important to see... you... it's important to stop expecting to find some sort of hidden kind of blitz or for... for... for... for kind of moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, I saw it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is what people often expect there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it actually takes time to shake that off, because everything points at something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every meditation technique, every print, every practice, something you're going to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not about seeing it, it's about doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what you're doing, apparently, doesn't seem to have any result.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people can't achieve it by accident.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people can't develop their mind accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you might do it once accidentally, or twice accidentally, or five times accidentally, but you see no apparent verification that Putujana would recognize as something worth pursuing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you... you just... it's inconceivable that you would stick to it and keep repeating it on and on and on, unless somebody you have faith in tells you to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you repeat it and you repeat nothing, nothing, nothing, nothing, nothing, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you look back and you realize, oh, actually, it's not nothing anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mind has changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the similarity of that axe handle, how the work... the carpenter doesn't know how much it has been wasted, but he just keeps using it until it thins out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to keep going and you have to keep in check with the patients that kind of expectation to, oh, I got it now, I had it, I had it for, I had it like for this second.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because the background remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just want to train how to start discerning it as background.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you start discerning it as background, as I said, you don't even need all these suttas that we have.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need very few.
[SPEAKER_00]: And things will become clearer, because you now have a basis for discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you pair all that effort of discerning the Bhagavan, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: effort of properly developing mindfulness, if you pair that with reading the suttas and try investigating the meaning, reading in the Veda, things like that, that will make you think about it, then, yeah, you are basically making quite different progress.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I think you nicely visited somewhere as the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what happened to me that I was, you know, it's something new and, you know, it was very exciting.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's some unusual things happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, and, but I think I've said, uh, uh, this kind of talking to myself and bring it, bring it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I not actually bringing it to foreground now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might sort of talk to yourself as kind of picking it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you don't need to keep talking to yourself if it's still up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in the suttas, when the monks would try to understand something, they would kind of say it loud, vicely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, oh, first jhāna, first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they bring their mind, kind of, through that utterance, through that designation, and then the mind starts thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They like to keep saying, what's the first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind is directed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like you direct it, and then you push it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, that's possible for somebody who has developed mind to that extent, that he can actually contemplate on the basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's sort of a practice, really, that's... as I said before, it's about doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, again, important to repeat, because if you focus on actually just repetition and developing the attitude, then
[SPEAKER_00]: The content of the experience becomes secondary, becomes irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, even if you have something, some lofty sort of sublime new experience, now you're not fooled by it, you're not taken by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not overwhelmed by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whether it's a lofty experience, whether it's lowly, whether it's mundane, whether it's upper mundane, whether it's normal, whether it's a novelty kind of rare experience, experience is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you stop being concerned with the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can't... you can't crave those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't crave the nature or experiences present.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of indifferent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you also overcome any mystical attitudes or any sort of... sort of mystical, um... pleasurable revelations and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The revelations you get are revelations of your insight that are based upon efforts to understand and... and the understanding being developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's very nicely summarized, because that what I was basically doing all these years, I was just being caught up in experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It never somehow... if it's reading these sutras, or whatever, it never... you know, and it's there, actually, but it never opened to me, actually, to look on the structure of experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the structure of the experience is nothing other than the same nature of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And nature, the Buddha said himself, that's what he called the whole teaching, he called dhamma, in the same... using the same word he uses for nature of particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's dhamma, dhamma with capital D. It's nothing other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I now understand, what you are talking about, basically, the past cannot be found in the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's by understanding the nature of that which appears, the nature of the five... and it's... in other...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, in many sutras it's said, by understanding the nature of the five aggregates, there is no room for upādāna anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop holding them and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, as you can see, it is simple once you kind of get the notion of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, of course, it's not simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not elaborate intellectually.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very, very concise and very direct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, unless you see it, you won't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even if somebody talks about it, general, about the nature, same nature of experience, it's peripheral of experience, it's nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, even if somebody talks about it, if a person doesn't have the attention they can spend
[SPEAKER_00]: To the actual and peripheral simultaneously present, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: if he doesn't have yonison manasikāra, the one that can include it...
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, we're just seeing it as another method, as another thing, as another technique, as another foreground thing that he can adhere to mechanically, and it will lead him to results.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can come up with the right instructions, but he won't read them rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't understand them rightly, because he doesn't have... his mind doesn't have the span to recognize that instruction applies simultaneously, but at different layers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, we...
[SPEAKER_01]: I've known you a few years already, so we already have a few perspectives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just two days ago, actually, I just got at least, let's say, slightly what you are talking about, before it really is... And the whole, like, parthita-sampāda, for example, refers exactly to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that simultaneous presence of the two different, sort of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things, in your experience, not to the same extent, but they're simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: One is foreground, one is background.
[SPEAKER_00]: nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, upādāna, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter what the content of the foreground is, nor what the content of the peripheral is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the structure is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what patisthamapādā is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're going with the grain of that nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go how it pushes you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go with the grain of patisthamapādā.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means ignorance is being maintained
[SPEAKER_00]: That simultaneous sort of principle of that simultaneously present nature, you go against.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's upādā, means ignorance is not generated anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: The content is relevant in a secondary sense, initially, in terms of abstaining from unwholesome content, unwholesome engagement, things based on sensuality, ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's just so that you can actually see through the nature of the content and then stop being concerned with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how ārmān goes beyond good and bad, how people often like to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so in that sense, you can you can transcend, you can you can sort of overcome any influence content can have over you by understanding the nature of that which contains that content.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just have to be, sort of, patient and really keep, sort of, finding energy to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, it's not, you know, you won't get any novelty, sort of, release energy, whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what people nowadays on the retreats... Because it's really on to you to develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And initially, seemingly, there is absolutely no
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why faith needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have faith that that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: You try to also kind of supplement that faith with any sort of intellectual clarity and understanding you can get in regard to the message that you're supposed to be applying, and then you just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep doing it, and keep doing it, and keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But still, you can basically do your formal meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just about this different approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just can use like vehicle, ānāpānasati, or movements of the bodhi, in regards to that, like this and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I still, you know... Basically, you just... All you need to do is something that's not too distracting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're walking up and down, why don't you just go for a walk?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you know, here it might be a bit more because it's a rough terrain.
[SPEAKER_00]: A lot to look out for.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, say, like in England...
[SPEAKER_00]: You could just go on those country lanes for a walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't think about where you're stepping, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can just fully commit to repetition of that contemplation, because you remain in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body... everything is already there, given for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The things you need to work with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't need to be, sort of, fabricating on top of it, and giving priority to some sort of focusing method and techniques and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually, as you can see, focusing works on particularizing whatever has a reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to learn how to gen... like, see the general, in regard to whatever is already particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you basically go opposite way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't... you don't want to be caught up in the experience and be completely lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you have pain in your knees, weird sensations in your back, itchy elbows, what is in common to all of those things?
[SPEAKER_00]: The body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing other than a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a mental image.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if a mental image, if you're mindful of it, it will stand for that which body is in your present experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you lose mindfulness, it becomes an abstract thought of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you need to kind of reconnect it to to your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you just need to be mindful of it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will sort of re-emerge as that which your body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't know anything without a mental image in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, it's... it seems like you can't even talk about something that would not exist without... because that's already a mental image.
[SPEAKER_00]: A phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where you have to start recognizing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not kind of following weird sort of itchiness and sensations in your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that kind of seems like a solution because you actually forget about a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: They are just lost in the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the thing is, sooner or later, depending how much effort you put in, you're going to get used to it, in particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: way of looking at things, that focusing, and then that novelty, and that release of that of that novelty, kind of, it's a new thing, it's a new discovery, it's gonna fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you need to do it harder, or find something else, or go on a longer retreat, or become even stricter vipassana practitioner, and whatnot, just to intensify it even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you just keep going further, and further, and further, in that wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you can have somebody understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just even without any of that, just... Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because understanding is in that general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he understands things rightly, he understood the nature, he might not necessarily be mindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, he needs to have a mindfulness to some degree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, for the mind to remain present and compose, saṃsāra samādhi, uh, for him to see things clearly through that understanding and through that instructions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sometimes they would just discuss the dhamma and mind would enter samādhi based on the discussion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not based on some sort of, you know, sharing of the mutual energy that kind of passes from me to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, just understanding the same setup, the same structure that results in mind reaching an equilibrium.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can we still define mindfulness as awareness of the present moment experience?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but mindfulness sort of should allow
[SPEAKER_00]: a degree of forgetfulness, as well, of the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just like a constant un-present, un-present, un-present, un-present, because whether you do un-present, even what you're forgetting is in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to discern that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how mindfulness becomes unshakable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, when you forget things and come back from it, the basis remains unaffected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whether you forget, you forget in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you think about the past, you think in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you plan about the future, you plan in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, it's not optional for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are stuck in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the recognition of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people don't recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They try to fabricate it with their effort and with a forceful attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm present, I'm present, I'm present, I'm present.
[SPEAKER_00]: One, two, three, four, five, oh, forgot.
[SPEAKER_00]: One, two, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your presence means things are already enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a discerning of those three characteristics, arising in manifest, ceasing in manifest, eh... persistent or changing in manifest, mindfulness is established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just... Not by active effort, because you are already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your effort is not present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize it's redundant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether I want or not, I'm in the present moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully understanding that, that cannot be... that cannot be disturbed, even when you... when you... when you forget about things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when forgetting and remembering ceases to sort of induce ignorance, in the sense of you forget that things endure, you forget that you are not the center of experience, you forget that things don't really need you for their operating, the five aggregates exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, without you, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you forget those things, then, when you remember, you remember with yourself, you remember with your craving, you remember with your conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the mindfulness needs to be developed to the extent necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the knowledge of forgetfulness and non-forgetfulness needs to be developed to the extent necessary to include both, so that neither will induce the confusion from beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, also, it seems that, basically, thinking or thoughts is just
[SPEAKER_01]: But it can be used as another, let's say, object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's in the same... but still seems to me that the body is actually better.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you have to start...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think starting with the mind will be too hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, as the Buddha said, a practitioner can, you know, understand the nature of the body and even remove any passion in regards to it, but understanding the impermanence of the mind and so on, it's too hard, because it moves too quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same principle, it's the same nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't want to start with the body because energies are hidden in the body and you're going to release some trapped ignorance that's somewhere in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start just because it's easier to see, but you do extrapolate the same principle and start applying it to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, ultimately, it's the thoughts, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to deal with something that will deal with both your mind and your body, you need to deal with your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's too hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you begin with the obvious thoughts of your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that you can start seeing the nature of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that then, thoughts of your mind, thoughts in the mind, thoughts that are not necessarily concerned with the body, that can also be included through understanding the same nature of a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh, do you have access to body only through, eh, mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, see, that's not... the question kind of already implies a certain answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh, the body is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way you can have the experience of the body is because of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means the mind is then... cannot be separated from the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the body... well, you can't even say the body if the mind is not already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, the mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It defines it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It designates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, if there is nothing there, the mind would not be able to designate anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there is... there is the form rūpa that is necessary for the whole presence of nāma and that designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so basically it means... Yeah, the problem is now... See, when I said there is rūpa, when you think that thought there is rūpa, you think that's the actual rūpa, but no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just another nāma in regard to that because of which that nāma is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have... that's how you start conceiving the rūpa, in the experience, when the thoughts in regard to rūpa are regarded as that which rūpa is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in... if you experience rūpa, if you experience bodhi, it's not the bodhi, it's... Well, no, see, no, that's a problem already.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you're denying rūpa, which is another form of affirming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, basically, he conceives form, he conceives in form, he conceives apart from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, no, it's not the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's both the body and not the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's neither body nor not the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, he keeps referring to the body, which he still means... means, basically, he still assumes that he can relate to that which body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, he can relate to that rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, thinking that you can relate to that rūpa means you already conceived it as relatable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you must basically catch it peripherally, what we were talking...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't catch it in a moment, because that's already the product of your conceiving or misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to understand it peripherally, whereby...
[SPEAKER_00]: In thinking, there is just thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: In seeing, there is just seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In heard, there is just heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: there is no... not too much, not too little of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is not giving to the rūpa or taking away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just fully understood that this thought stands upon the basis that rūpa is, but even that thought does not, for you, induce assumption that that's what that rūpa is, because that wouldn't... well, basically, that would be overshooting the mark.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be like you accessing that which you cannot access.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by not knowing that you cannot access, you access it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you maintain its existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how rūpa finds a footing in your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: You create it, you give it, you maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good, very good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm glad it's clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one thing, another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, now I... Now I lost the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I had the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: My comeback.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we were talking about two things, not concealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts, experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my gosh, I have such a question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Coming back to the section of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, we have these three characteristics, and what I got from you is basically that the understanding of them comes, all of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like a sequence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, I was thinking that you must... that by understanding anicca, you come to understanding dukkha, and then... You go to the next one to understand anicca.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's one insight that you can develop to have these three characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might not necessarily be equally discerning all the characteristics, but you see them all to some extent, hence the insight is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same with the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just four aspects of the one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like one, and then you go to the second, and then, after a few days, you reach the third.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically just four ways of laying out every every aspect of that one insight, which is freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one who is free from suffering knows what the suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he doesn't know what the suffering is, he wouldn't be able to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows how that suffering arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows how that suffering came to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows how that suffering ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he knows what he needs to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all in one insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you want to teach that one insight to somebody, this is the ultimate way, the most accurate, precise way to lay it out, as for aspects that need to be covered.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why there's another sort of... Oh, I forgot.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it kind of breaks it down to, like, three, you need to develop three, and the kind of, eh... Four Noble Truths become, like, twelve path or steps, so to speak, where every truth needs to be developed fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have the four aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: To fully develop four aspects, I... like... and each aspect can be developed three-fold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you get twelve.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, you get four and twelve.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not like one, two, three, four, five.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just one,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But some aspects can be more prominent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you might be clear in some aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that means, basically, there is still some ignorance left.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you fully develop all four aspects, you'll be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means Ārya does not have all four aspects fully developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has them to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he has them.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, that's just an approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just one approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not necessary in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to... As I said, it's not... it's not a fixed method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... there's just one goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said, he only teaches suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the ocean has only the taste of salt, no matter where it is, so he teaches freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter what approach you take, no matter through what sutta you arrive at understanding, no matter how different it might sound, those are not all methods you have to cover.
[SPEAKER_00]: They all point at the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you arrive at the same thing, that's all it matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody arrives at the same thing through contemplation of the nature of suffering, craving in regard to it and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then he becomes free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: He becomes an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody, you know, with a different mind, arrives to understanding of this simultaneous principle, which is patitsa upādāna, of the actual and peripheral, he becomes free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same result.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sometimes, that's what the Navarra meant, that sometimes even people with the right view might actually hesitate if they were to describe Pāṭicca Samupādā as twelve factors.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's a subtle thing to see, and they might have arrived differently at the freedom from suffering, and then they never thought of Pāṭicca Samupādā in that relevant manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: They thought it, oh, it's just some explanation, and they don't care about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they arrived at freedom from suffering through some completely different approach.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, that's why
[SPEAKER_00]: Some have arrived only through like a single kind of approach that they really committed to and had faith in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some arrived through discernment of many different approaches that kind of brought mind to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And their wisdom, basis for wisdom, is greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they can teach better.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can understand better.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not all of them can.
[SPEAKER_00]: But some of them can only teach in a manner that they reached.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean that they're less.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the Buddha said it doesn't matter how you reach it or how wide you have to circle in order to reach it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is to reach it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why the
[SPEAKER_00]: Faith type, the wisdom type, and the kind of a meditation sort of translation, meditation type, one through samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of them is better than the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one who is the best is the one who becomes an arahant, and any of them can become an arahant on the basis of these three things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not like, oh, he's a better arahant because he arrived through wisdom, and then he's a worse arahant because he arrived through faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both are arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we were also talking about this anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you say it again?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is actually anicca?
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, it would be hard to undo the notion of material sort of scientific impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when people say it's impermanent, they expect it's destruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they often use that as a proof of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once something has been destroyed, you say, yes, truly, look how these things are all impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... not just that that doesn't make any any kind of relevant sense for the freedom of the sense of self, but also you can't even apply it in that sense, because it would require you to kill yourself, to destroy yourself, to see yourself as not yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to see you're not self, you actually require the phenomenon of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: To see it as not belonging to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you destroy it, even before you see it, means you completely, sort of... well, you entirely, just entirely block your own progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly... you remove any basis for discernment of that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should really think...
[SPEAKER_00]: Anicca, as I said, it's a kind of wide basis in Sanskrit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anicca means everlasting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even the definition, by the way, of permanent, if you look at the English definition, means lasting until it comes to an end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it has permanent presence until it disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole notion of eternal,
[SPEAKER_00]: It gets kind of preached into that sense of self, and then, oh, eternal, non-eternal, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that can be too abstract for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on a more practical level, if you want to look at anicca, it means, basically, out of your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That which is present, but cannot be owned, cannot be truly in your possession, in your mastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize everything exercises that degree of resistance to some degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything exercises resistance to some degree to you, which means everything shares the nature of anicca to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's that varying degrees of anicca that confuse people.
[SPEAKER_00]: In thinking that things that are kind of exercising less of a independence, kind of resistance attitude towards you, you confuse them as yours, because it's resisting you less.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not a question of not resisting you at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a question of, basically, things are impermanent and less impermanent, but they're still impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words,
[SPEAKER_00]: Things are out of your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some of them more so, some of them less so, but fundamentally, none of them is fully in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all it's... all it takes, just to recognize that then, ah, so then this whole notion of self, there is the notion of absolute control.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason self cannot be based upon partial control.
[SPEAKER_00]: If self recognizes partial control elsewhere, it means it's taking full control somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's established upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might dismiss everything saying, I know this is mine because I don't control it, but maybe that very thought is something you think you control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your sense of self remains lingering to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you need to include a peripheral, the general nature whereby you kind of scoop it all up and then discern it within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you keep chasing where yourself is established, you won't find it, because it's always going to slip to the next thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, anicca, as that Sanskrit anicca also has one of the meanings, is dear and internal, personal, personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, contemplate the nature of personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take something that you... oh, this is personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to say that, what do you refer to?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I refer to as personal?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would see, kind of, if you were to describe it phenomenologically, that experience, you would be referring to something that's close, almost inside, in relation to the outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something right here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why it's personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you took possession of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you guarded it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you kind of sheltered it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you recognize that none of the things can be personal in that sense, that's how you disown it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what anicca is.
[SPEAKER_00]: By recognizing that none of that can be personal, that any of that can come to an end at any time, and you recognize that while the thing is still present, that's how you sort of... well, you recognize danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're holding on to something that will sort of pull you to death because of your holding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you, you know, you have to die, just because you're gripping on to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you recognize that
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things that I hold dear, for that very reason, just for that very reason, can be a result of my demise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's very dangerous, but at the same time, it becomes very liberating recognizing that, because then you let go of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you keep... remain surrounded with your possessions and stuff, none of them will be regarded on that personal level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something happens, if you lose your house, if you lose this, if you lose your friend,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind will not be affected, it won't be shattered by that, because it has withdrawn, recalled away from it, before it disappeared, before it took you away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what anicca is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where, again, automatically, by recognizing anicca properly, you recognize the suffering in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, just for that reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because it might be a very good thing, might be a very happy thing, family, children, all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: By automatically, or simultaneously better, by recognizing suffering, you don't regard that as dear, you don't regard it as personal, you don't regard that as mine.
Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in order to have that attitude of mine, that lingering notion of mine, belonging to me, you need to see it as personal.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see it as dear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see it as worthy, as pleasurable, as non-dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you say that actually, you know, the... what you consider to be self is not yourself, if I summarize
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only point is just...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to summarize even slightly more accurately, but you can see that, that which you take to be yourself, is a real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I wanted to ask.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to remove your sense of ownership in regard to that notion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that notion is still basically there, but you don't consider... See, but you can't see that notion directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why this whole point of training your mind in peripheral recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you start including that vague notion of self, that vague notion of ownership, that vague notion of master external to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start including into that peripheral that you see it's present while the actual has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind becomes established in that peripheral, you realize self never appears as a direct object, because it wouldn't be the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, in order to tackle the self, you need to see the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see the phenomenal self.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to see the phenomenal self, you need to learn how to see an ambiguous phenomena as ambiguous phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not overdefine it into that which you expect it to be, but basically see it how it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: This kind of weird
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of hard to describe, put in words, hard to put a finger on, notion, sense of self, of master.
[SPEAKER_00]: They might have, kind of, a memory of your face attached to it, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But anyway, it's a sort of a ambiguous phenomena that nevertheless is present as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learning how to see peripheral, you learn how to recognize these phenomena for what they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when you see there's that peripheral, you don't interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't make it actual.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't redefine it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to destroy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, atta becomes un-atta.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The self becomes not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't become no-self, like there was never self.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there was.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there was never self, you wouldn't have had the self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just a mistake of ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when Yogīvara said, when a person disappears, or tujana, when the sense attavāda disappears, individual remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that vague general notion, basically, might remain, but it won't be regarded as the supreme master of the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, above all, it won't be regarded as independent of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be regarded as an independent of the experience as a whole, actual and peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be seen as just a, basically, sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why individuals vary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Individuals are different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people, some people sort of are... Like, arahants vary.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't turn into the same identical blank five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Different individual, different preferences, different notions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no assumption in regards to the individual, assumption of ownership, assumption of self, and then, obviously, assumption of the self-view as a completely independent sense of self, completely independent of any of the five aggregates that serve as a manager and master of them externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It ties in together nicely when you're speaking from the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like many different sort of, oh, wow, that's really clever.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's just one thing explaining millions of different ways, but the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same point, the same principle, the same image, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you must basically see that this point is not just like object of your thinking, but it's pointing to the structure of the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I basically got from our... Yeah, because if it's just an object of your thinking, that means everything else underneath it is completely left untouched.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot ever reach the end of the suffering if you just make it another object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.